{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "John Cobb died while on a speedboat in this body of water. The crannog of Cherry Island lies in this body of water, on whose shores lie Urquhart Castle and the town of Port Augustus. The Falls of Foyers feed into this body of water. The “Surgeon’s Photograph” was a hoax purportedly depicting a creature that lived in this lake. For ten points, name this Scottish body of water, purportedly home to a cryptocreature named Nessie.",
      "answer": "Loch Ness or Lake Ness"
    },
    {
      "question": "Albert Schweitzer won the 1952 Nobel Peace Prize in part for building one of these institutions in Lambar´en´e, Gabon. The poor conditions in one of these buildings in Scutari led Isambard Kingdom Brunel to build a prefabricated one of these that was shipped to Renkioi during the Crimean War. One of these in Kunduz was attacked in 2015; that airstrike was requested by anti-Taliban forces and carried out by the US Air Force. For ten points, name these institutions built in warzones by Doctors Without Borders.",
      "answer": "hospital"
    },
    {
      "question": "This island’s native population, known for long, wavy beards, rebelled in Shakushain’s Revolt. This island’s port of Hakodate [hah-ko-dah-tay] was the capital of its breakway Republic of Ezo. The first Asian Winter Olympics were held on this island at Sapporo. The Seikan Tunnel connects this home of the Ainu people to its southern neighbor, Honshu. The Sea of Okhtosk is north of, for ten points, what northernmost of Japan’s four main islands?",
      "answer": "Hokkaido"
    },
    {
      "question": "Marty Glickman claimed that his removal from an Olympic team in favor of this man was a political capitulation by Avery Brundage. This man provided the “greatest 45 minutes in sports” by breaking three world records and tying another at a Big Ten conference meet. This athlete controversially claimed that “it was our president who snubbed me” in response to having not shaken Adolf Hitler’s hand on the medal podium. For ten points, name this African-American runner who won four gold medals at the 1936 Summer Olympics.",
      "answer": "James Cleveland Jesse Owens"
    },
    {
      "question": "Zia ul-Haq led a coup against one leader with this surname in Operation Fair Play. That leader with this surname was later arrested for the murder of Ahmed Kasuri and executed after a sham trial. That leader’s daughter was exiled on corruption charges for nine years before Pervez Musharraf granted her amnesty to run in 2007 elections; during that campaign, she was assassinated in Rawalpindi. For ten points, give this surname shared by Zulfikar Ali and Benazir, two Prime Ministers of Pakistan.",
      "answer": "Bhutto"
    },
    {
      "question": "Gary Gordon and Randy Shughart were killed while defending one of these vehicles near the Bakaara market. A haboob prevented eight of these vehicles, nicknamed “Sea Stallions,” from successfully completing Operation Eagle Claw, much to the embarrassment of Jimmy Carter. During the Battle of Mogadishu, two of these vehicles were grounded by RPG fire. The Sikorsky Black Hawk is, for ten points, what type of military aircraft, which uses rotary wings?",
      "answer": "helicopter"
    },
    {
      "question": "After fighting at Sevastopol, this city was to be attacked by the Schwerer Gustav railgun. An attack on this city was led by Ritter von Leeb and carried out during Operation Northern Light. A supply route called the Road of Life helped resupply this city by ferrying supplies across Lake Lagoda. During the relief of this city, the Baltic fleet fired on troops from Army Group North after breaking 900 days of siege. For ten points, name this city, named for the first leader of the Soviet Union.",
      "answer": "Leningrad"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man called one of his works a “proper Vehicle for conveying Instruction among the common People;” that work was published under the name Saunders. He detailed his fleeing from Boston to New York and his writing of the Silence Dogood essays in an autobiography published in 1791. The aphorism “early to bed, early to rise/makes a man healthy, wealthy, and wise” is attributed to, for ten points, what author of Poor Richard’s Almanac, an American founding father?",
      "answer": "Ben Franklin"
    },
    {
      "question": "This building was constructed with the help of a donation from the governor Zerubbabel. This building, where a table always held a dozen loaves of “showbread,” was the cultural and religious center of the Hasmonean Kingdom, which gained its independence following the Maccabean Revolt. This structure was destroyed on Tisha B’Av in 70 AD, and the Dome of the Rock was built on its former location. The Western, or “Wailing,” Wall is the only remaining portion of, for ten points, what Jewish holy building?",
      "answer": "Second Temple of Jerusalem"
    },
    {
      "question": "Wisconsin’s John Blaine was the only senator to vote against ratification of this agreement, which the Senate interpreted to protect the right to self-defense. Sixty-two countries ultimately signed this agreement, which was criticized for having no effective means of enforcement, as seen by Italy’s invasion of Ethiopia in 1935. For ten points, name this 1928 agreement, named for a US Secretary of State and French Foreign Minister, whose signatories renounced the use of war in national policy.",
      "answer": [
        "Kellogg-Briand Pact",
        "Pact of Paris"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Childe Wills, Joseph Galamb, and Eugene Farkas designed this product, which was “large enough for the family, but small enough for the individual to run and care for.” Scraps of wood from its production led to the formation of Kingsford Charcoal. After six years of production, its inventor decided it can be “painted any color [the customer] wants, so long as it’s black.” Factories in Highland Park and Detroit made, for ten points, what affordable automobile that was phased out by Ford in 1927 in favor of the Model A?",
        "answer": "Ford Model T"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1914, Ford shocked the industry by announcing this action, which took the form of a bonus given to workers who avoided “violations” like drinking, domestic abuse, and keeping an unclean home.",
        "answer": "paying workers five dollars a day"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One side’s monarch in this war was captured at the Skirmish at Bender. Grengam and Gangut were two major naval battles in this war, in which Augustus the Strong was defeated. The Cossack leader Ivan Mazeppa switched sides in this war, which was ended by the Treaty of Nystad. One side attacked in a blinding snowstorm to win the Battle of Narva in this war, though Charles XII would later be defeated at Poltava by Peter the Great. For ten points, name this early 18th century war in which Russia soundly defeated Sweden.",
        "answer": "Great Northern War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Peter the Great overestimated Russian strength in the war when he turned and attacked this empire’s ports on the Black Sea.",
        "answer": "Ottoman Empire"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this region, Rachel Corrie was run over by a bulldozer while trying to prevent a house demolition. Ariel Sharon launched a unilateral disengagement from this region, which is home to the currently defunct Yasser Arafat International Airport. In 2014, Operation Protective Edge was launched against this region after the kidnapping and murder of three teenage Israeli settlers. Hamas currently controls, for ten points, what Mediterranean-bordering “strip” once held by Israel?",
        "answer": "Gaza Strip"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The aforementioned kidnapping and murder of three Israeli teens sparked an Israeli search operation that was given this name, referencing Cain’s response to God. ANSWER:(Operation)Brother’sKeeper(acceptelaborations, suchas“AmImy brother’skeeper?”) (4) This country’s navy was the target of Operation Praying Mantis in retaliation for its mine striking the USS Samuel B. Roberts. Terrorists killed 422 people in the Cinema Rex fire, which was blamed on SAVAK, this country’s secret police. Allan Dulles planned Operation Ajax to remove Mohammed Mossadegh from power in this country, from where Reza Pahlavi was exiled. For ten points, name this country where a 1979 revolution brought Ayatollah Khomeini to power in Tehran.",
        "answer": "Iran BONUS: This 1963 westernizing movement in Iran supported land reform. Its name reflects the bloodless nature of the revolution, though the arrest of Khomeini during it triggered violent riots. ANSWER: White Revolution"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This character claims to possess an “itemized list of thirty years of disagreements” in one appearance. One character aggravatedly notes that this man wrote 51 separate essays in a work that was only supposed to run 25 total essays. This character is introduced as a “bastard orphan” in the opening song of his musical, which is narrated by his eventual assassin, Aaron Burr. For ten points, name this protagonist of a 2015 Lin-Manuel Miranda musical and first Secretary of the Treasury.",
        "answer": "Alexander Hamilton"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Alexander Hamilton marries Eliza, the middle daughter of a man with this last name. A song named after Eliza and her sisters with this last name occurs in Act I of the musical.",
        "answer": "Schuyler"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "With Rufus Isaacs, this man was accused of speculating on inside knowledge during the Marconi scandal of 1913. This man addressed the Shell Crisis during World War I as Minister of Munitions, and he succeeded Lord Kitchener as Secretary of State for War in 1916. This only Prime Minister to have spoken fluent Welsh was among the “Big Four” at the Versailles Conference. For ten points, name this Liberal British Prime Minister who presided over the end of World War I.",
        "answer": "David Lloyd George"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Italian member of the Big Four quarreled with his foreign minister, Sidney Sonnino, left the conference without signing.",
        "answer": "Vittorio Orlando"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This author wrote a work subtitled “The Long Parliament” about the English Civil War. Another work by this author states that “dark and erroneous doctrines” are used by a “confederacy of deceivers” to help create a “Kingdom of Darkness.” That work by this author states that there only exist three types of commonwealth, of which absolute monarchy is the best option. For ten points, name this author who described life as “nasty, brutish, and short” in Leviathan.",
        "answer": "Thomas Hobbes"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Thomas Hobbes’ Leviathan is one of the earliest works that discusses this concept. This concept, which describes how individuals must sacrifice individual rights to their rulers, also titles a work by Jean Jacques Rousseau.",
        "answer": "social contract"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man provided Harry Truman with a list of 12,000 Americans suspected of disloyalty, though Truman refused action. After press coverage of the Apalachin Meeting in 1957, this man began attacking the U.S. Mafia. Clyde Tolson very briefly succeeded him in his highest post, after a 37-year tenure during which he coordinated the arrests of John Dillinger and Al Capone. For ten points, name this first director of the FBI.",
        "answer": "J. Edgar Hoover"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Hoover’s COINTELPRO program attempted to have this man, who he called the “most notorious liar” in the U.S., arrested for extramarital affairs and communist leanings. The FBI sent a letter to this civil rights leader trying to convince him to commit suicide.",
        "answer": "Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. or MLK"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "American Expansion",
      "prompt": "In the history of American land acquisition, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "French emperor who sold Louisiana to America.",
          "answer": "Napoleon Bonaparte"
        },
        {
          "question": "Northernmost state in New England, whose border was clarified by the Webster-Ashburton Treaty.",
          "answer": "Maine"
        },
        {
          "question": "River that marks the border between the US and Mexico between El Paso and the Gulf of Mexico.",
          "answer": "Rio Grande or Rio Bravo del Norte"
        },
        {
          "question": "46th state admitted to the Union, having been an unorganized Indian Territory until the early 20th century.",
          "answer": "Oklahoma"
        },
        {
          "question": "President who signed the bill officially annexing Texas.",
          "answer": "James K. Polk"
        },
        {
          "question": "Caribbean island group purchased from Denmark just before the U.S. entered World War I.",
          "answer": "U.S. Virgin Islands"
        },
        {
          "question": "1819 treaty with Spain that gave Florida to the U.S.",
          "answer": "Adams-Onis Treaty"
        },
        {
          "question": "Price, within 10%, that the U.S. paid to Russia to purchase “Seward’s Folly.”",
          "answer": [
            "$7,200,000",
            "any answer between $6,480,000 and $7,920,000"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Ominous Warnings",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Roman dictator killed, as predicted, on the Ides of March?",
          "answer": "Gaius Julius Caesar"
        },
        {
          "question": "2005 hurricane that Robert Ricks predicted would make most of New Orleans “UNINHABITABLE FOR WEEKS...PERHAPS LONGER.”",
          "answer": "Hurricane Katrina"
        },
        {
          "question": "2012 “superstorm” that flooded New Jersey and New York, shortly after the NWS begged “IF YOU ARE RELUCTANT [to evacuate], THINK OF YOUR LOVED ONES”.",
          "answer": "Hurricane or Superstorm Sandy"
        },
        {
          "question": "German leader whose abdication was predicted 20 years in advance by Otto von Bismarck.",
          "answer": "Kaiser Wilhelm II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Physicist who quoted “I am become death, the destroyer of worlds” after the Trinity nuclear test.",
          "answer": "J. Robert Oppenheimer"
        },
        {
          "question": "Daughter of Priam who was given the power of prophecy, but the curse of never being believed.",
          "answer": "Cassandra"
        },
        {
          "question": "Soviet premier who refused to mobilize in spite of intelligence about Operation Barbarossa.",
          "answer": "Joseph Stalin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Tragedy coincidentally foreshadowed by Morgan Robertson’s 1898 novella Futility.",
          "answer": "sinking of the RMS Titanic"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Alcohol",
      "prompt": "In the history of alcohol, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "13-year period of American history when sale and transport of alcohol was banned by the 18th Amendment.",
          "answer": "Prohibition"
        },
        {
          "question": "Constitutional amendment that ended that ban.",
          "answer": "21st Amendment"
        },
        {
          "question": "Process by which a fermented beverage, like vodka or moonshine, is purified by selective evaporation?",
          "answer": [
            "distillation",
            "word forms"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Type of sparkling wine supposedly invented in France by the monk Dom Perignon?",
          "answer": "champagne"
        },
        {
          "question": "1791 rebellion in western Pennsylvania against Alexander Hamilton’s tax on spirits.",
          "answer": "Whiskey Rebellion"
        },
        {
          "question": "Term for an ancient Greek drinking party, which names and is depicted in a Platonic dialogue about the purpose of love.",
          "answer": "Symposium"
        },
        {
          "question": "Greek wine whose flavor and name comes from the resin used to seal the bottle in ancient times.",
          "answer": "retsina"
        },
        {
          "question": "Macedonian officer killed in a drunken argument by Alexander the Great, whom he had saved at the Battle of the Granicus.",
          "answer": "Cleitus the Black"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man forced Henri, duc de Rohan, to agree to the Peace of Alais. Pere Joseph was a prominent ally of this man, nicknamed for the grey robe that he wore as a Capuchin friar. (20 pts)",
        "Marie de Medici’s exile was due to her involvement in a conspiracy to remove this leader, the Day of the Dupes. The siege of the Huguenot castle of La (10 pts)",
        "Rochelle was led by this man, who was also known as the “Red Eminence”. He was succeeded by Mazarin in his highest post. For ten points, name this powerful chief minister of Louis XIII, a French cardinal."
      ],
      "answer": "Cardinal Richelieu"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This year was the last time a major party was undecided on its Presidential nominee at the start of the convention. One presidential candidate in this election year defeated Arizona senator Morris Udall in the primaries, and gave an interview admitting that he had (20 pts)",
        "“lust in his heart.” The incumbent in this race was damaged by his assertion that there was “no Soviet domination of Eastern Europe” and his (10 pts)",
        "pardoning of Richard Nixon for Watergate. For ten points, name this election year in which Gerald Ford was defeated by peanut farmer Jimmy Carter?"
      ],
      "answer": "Presidential election of 1976"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This region was occupied during the Lesser Wrath of 1743 after the Hats’ War. An 1866 famine in this nation and its western neighbor was the last naturally caused one in Europe. After World War II, this country secured its safety by signing the (20 pts)",
        "YYA Treaty with its larger, eastern neighbor, which this country fought in the Continuation and Winter Wars. A (10 pts)",
        "sniper from this country was nicknamed the “White Death” for his kill count and helped avenge this country’s loss of Karelia to the USSR. For ten points, name this Scandinavian country with capital at Helsinki."
      ],
      "answer": "Finland"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One participant in this event secured a commitment to have its lease at Port Arthur restored. This event featured a broken commitment from one party to reorganize the Lublin Committee “on a broader democratic basis,” and set the (20 pts)",
        "Curzon Line as the eastern border of Poland. This event, codenamed Argonaut, featured one participant’s pledge to attack (10 pts)",
        "Japan after the surrender of Nazi Germany, and it was followed up five months later by a meeting at Potsdam. For ten points, name this February 1945 meeting between Stalin, Churchill, and Roosevelt which took place on the Crimean Peninsula."
      ],
      "answer": "Yalta Conference"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This work concludes by recommending “an increasing sense that a thing won by breaking the rules of the game is not worth the winning.” It notes how “the speculative character of the business would be done away with” if its subject was able to control the (20 pts)",
        "shipping and refining aspects of production. This work grew out of interviews with Henry Rogers, and was followed by a two-part profile of its subject’s CEO. (10 pts)",
        "McClure’s magazine published a serialized version of, for ten points, what 1904 muckraking expos´e by Ida Tarbell into the inner workings of John D. Rockefeller’s company? ANSWER:TheHistoryof (the)StandardOilCompany(acceptanyanswerthatmentionstheHistory of Standard Oil, ignoring the usual “the title must be exact” rule, as it’s been published under many permutations; do not prompt on Standard Oil alone) (6) One performer of this instrument, who wrote “Nuages” and “Minor Swing,” collaborated with Stephane Grapelli and combined jazz with his native Romani music. A concerto for this instrument was inspired by the palace gardens of King Philip II in Aranjuez [air-an-weth] and was written by (+) Joaquin [wha-keen] Rodrigo. A performer of this instrument was inspired by the fight against Hitler to decorate his with the phrase “This Machine (*) Kills Fascists.” Django Reinhardt and the writer of “This Land Is Your Land,” Woody Guthrie, both played, for ten points, what instrument that has six strings and frets?"
      ],
      "answer": "guitar"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Charles II excused this scientist from having to become an ordained priest after he became a fellow of Trinity College. This scientist, whose ideas on the scientific method included his statement of “Hypotheses non fingo,” attributed his own success to “standing on the (20 pts)",
        "shoulders of giants.” This scientist retreated to his family home during an outbreak of plague in Cambridge, then developed a theory of (10 pts)",
        "optics and an inverse square law describing forces between any two objects. For ten points, name this scientist who developed three laws of motion and a law of universal gravitation."
      ],
      "answer": "Sir Isaac Newton"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A hand position often taken by this person has been nicknamed this person’s “diamond” and the “Triangle of Power.” This person attacked a former mentor after the 1999 “black money affair.” This leader claimed that attempts to build a multicultural society had (20 pts)",
        "“utterly failed” in 2010. This leader’s government helped bail out Hypo Real Estate, and this Time Magazine (10 pts)",
        "2015 Person of the Year has agreed to allow an “open-door” policy with regards to Syrian refugees entering her country. For ten points, name this head of the Christian Democratic Union and current Chancellor of Germany."
      ],
      "answer": "Angela Merkel"
    }
  ]
}